Robert C. Olby Collection 1951-1963 Mss.B.OL1
American Philosophical Society
Robert C. Olby Collection
1951-1963
Mss.B.OL1
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
The historian of science Robert C. Olby is a graduate of University College London and Oxford. Best known for his work on the history of genetics, especially the Bateson school, and for his study of the early history of molecular biology, Olby is currently a Research Professor in the History and Philosophy of Science at the University of Pittsburgh. He is the author of The Origins of Mendelism (1966), Charles Darwin (1967), The Path to the Double Helix (1974), and the Norton History of Biology. His current research is focused on the conceptual foundations of modern sensory neurophysiology and an intellectual biography of Francis Crick. The Olby Collection contains about 150 photocopies of correspondence and documents collected by Olby during research for The Path to the Double Helix. Among these is a copy of a manuscript by F. C. Crick and James D. Watson, "The Complementary Structure of Deoxyribonucleic Acid," prepared while Watson was at CalTech.
Olby, Robert C. (Robert Cecil), 1933-
Bibliography
Olby, Robert C., The Origins of Mendelism (London: Constable, 1966). Call no.: 575.1 OL1o.
Olby, Robert C., The Path to the Double Helix (Seattle: Univ. of Washington, 1974). Call no.: 574.19 OL1p.
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
This collection of letters, documents, and biographical information represents some of the materials Olby had gathered for his noted book The Path to the Double Helix (1974).
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
Brenner, Sydney Correspondence (1 item) 1960
Crick, Francis H. C. Correspondence (14 items) 1955-1963
Crick, Francis H. C. and Watson, James D. -- The Complementary Structure of Deoxyribonucleic Acid Manuscripts (28 pages) n.d.
Delbruck, Max Correspondence (2 items) 1953-1955
Franklin, Rosalind Correspondence (1 item) 1958
Gamow, George Correspondence (13 items) 1955-1962
Herriott, Roger Moss Correspondence (1 item) 1951
Hershey, Alfred Day Correspondence (1 item) 1951
Luria, Salvador Edward Correspondence (2 items) 1952-1953
Matthaei, Heinrich Correspondence (8 items) 1960, n.d.
Meselson, Matthew Correspondence (1 item) 1961
Olby, Robert Cecil -- Summary of Events Leading to Solution of DNA Structure Manuscripts (9 pages) n.d.
Pauling, Linus Correspondence (1 item) 1953
Rich, Alexander Correspondence (18 items) 1956-1963
Watson, James D. Correspondence (5 items) 1953-1955
Other Finding Aids note
The Robert Olby Papers are briefly described in Bentley Glass' A Guide to the Genetics Collections of the APS.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Robert C. Olby, June 1969 and October 1970 (acc. No. 1976-344ms and 1976-345ms).
Scope and Contents note
The Olby Collection (23 folders, approximately 97 items) is comprised almost entirely of photocopies of correspondence from scientists involved in the discovery of the double helical structure of DNA in 1953. The correspondents include Sydney Brenner, Francis Crick, Max Delbruck, Rosalind Franklin, Roger Herriott, Alfred Hershey, Salvadore Luria, Heinrich Matthaei, Matthew Meselson, Linus Pauling, Alexander Rich, and James Watson. The topics discussed within the correspondence include but are not limited to the structure of DNA, Pauling's theory, RNA backbone, Jonathan Warner, and the RNA central code.
Biographical/Historical note
A graduate of the University College London and Oxford, Robert C. Olby (b. 1933) earned a reputation as an innovative historian of genetics with the publication of first book The Origins of Mendelism in 1966. When a former undergraduate friend of his, John Preble, suggested that he study the history of molecular biology, Olby gained an introduction to Francis Crick, the British biophysicist and co-discoverer of the structure of DNA, who became both a scientific informant and close friend. Olby's The Path to the Double Helix (1974) provided an overview of the intellectual and institutional background that resulted in Watson and Crick's "physical and chemical account of the gene." In his introduction, Olby stated simply that his hope was that the book would "afford the historian, sociologist and scientist a guide to the source material relating to the origins of molecular biology, with special reference to DNA," but in fact it presented a masterful use of both primary written sources and oral histories. Ironically, Olby claimed that as a student at the University College London in the fifties, he could not remember hearing the word DNA ever being uttered.
Olby taught history of science at the University of Leeds from 1969-1993 and in the department of the History and Philosophy of Science at the University of Pittsburgh from 1994-2001, where he remains as Research Professor.
Brenner, Sydney; Crick, Francis, 1916-2004; Delbrück, Max; Franklin, Rosalind, 1920-1958; Gamow, George, 1904-1968; Herriott, Roger Moss, 1908-; Hershey, A. D., (Alfred Day), 1908-; Luria, S. E., (Salvador Edward), 1912-1991; Matthaei, Heinrich; Nirenberg, Marshall W.; Pauling, Linus, 1901-1994; Rich, Alexander; Watson, James Dewey, 1928-; DNA--Structure; Genetics; Molecular biology--History
- Robert C. Olby Collection, 1951-1963; 0.25 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - TLS Cy to Matthew Meselson, 1960 May 7; 1 item; Brenner, Sydney
    Scope and Contents note
    Regarding work of Jacques Monod and Francois Jacob.
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Cytogenetics; Jacob, Francois; Molecular genetics; Monod, Jacques
  - Crick, Francis H. C., 1955-1963; 14.0 Item(s)
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Biographical and personal data; Cytogenetics; Molecular genetics; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
    - Folder 1, 1955-1956; 6 items; Crick, Francis, 1916-2004
      Existance of deoxy-uracil in DNA; experiments on Collagen; new structure for polyglycine.
    - Folder 2, 1957-1960; 7 items; Crick, Francis, 1916-2004
      Polynucleotides; poly A; poly I + poly C; angle of hydroge hydrogen bond; DNA and RNA.
    - Folder 3. TLS Cy to Alex Rich, 1963 April 24; 1 item; Crick, Francis, 1916-2004
      Re: Rich's manuscript for Nature
  - The Complimentary Structure of Deoxyribonucleic Acid, n.d.; 28.0 p.; Crick, Francis, 1916-2004; Watson, James D., 1928-
    Prepared while Watson was at California Institute of Technology.
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Molecular genetics; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - Delbruck, Max, 1953-1955; 2.0 Item(s)
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Cytogenetics; Molecular genetics
    - Folder 1. TLS Cy to J. D. Watson, 1953 April 14; 1 item; Delbrück, Max
      DNA structure
    - Folder 2. TLS Cy to Alex and Jane Rich, 1955 November 9; 1 item; Delbrück, Max
      Rundle's RNA structure
  - ALS Cy to Alex Rich, 1958 March 16; 1 item; Franklin, Rosalind, 1920-1958
    Regarding tobacco mosaic virus (TMV).
    Biographical and personal data; Cytogenetics; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Molecular genetics
  - Gamow, George, 1955-1962; 13.0 Item(s)
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Biographical and personal data; Brenner, Sydney; Crick, Francis H. C.; Lectures, public speaking; Mazia, Daniel; Molecular genetics; Publication; Research support; RNA tie club; Travel -- Invitations, arrangements
    - Folder 1. ALS Cy to Alex Rich, 1955-1956; 8 items; Gamow, George, 1904-1968
      Discusses his book; trouble with proteins; divorce; research questions; official club circular; hellix vs. solenoid entanglement of chromosomes.
    - Folder 2. ALS Cy to Alex Rich, 1958-1962; 5 items; Gamow, George, 1904-1968
      On writing books; son Igor; soliciting opinion on the latest pronouncement by Francis Crick, Barnett, Brenner, and Watts-Tobin concerning "The General Nature of the Genetic Code."
  - TLS Cy to Alfred D. Hershey, 1951 November 16; 1 item; Herriott, Roger M.
    Amino acids in the phage but not in the ghosts; centrifugation of the ghosts; his own virus problem.
    Bacteriophage and viral genetics; Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Hershey, Alfred Day; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Molecular genetics
  - TL Cy to Roger M. Herriott, 1951 November 20; 1 item; Hershey, A. D., (Alfred Day), 1908-
    Results of the S 35 experiments; addressing Herriott's idea about the nucleic acid and Hershey's own opinion about intracellular phage.
    Bacteriophage and viral genetics; Herriott, Roger Moss; Molecular genetics
  - Correspondence, 1952-1953; 2 items; Luria, S. E., (Salvador Edward), 1912-1991
    S35 and protein and DNA; Linus Pauling's theory.
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Conferences and symposia; Cytogenetics; Molecular genetics; Pauling, Linus
  - Correspondence, 1960, n.d.; 8 items; Matthaei, Heinrich
    Materials obtained by Heinrich Matthaei, a coworker with Dr. Marshall W. Nirenberg, who won the Nobel prize for the discovery of DNA and collected by Olby for his book, The Path to the Double Helix
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Crick, Francis H. C.; Cytogenetics; History of biology, especially genetics; Mendel, Gregor; Molecular genetics; Nirenberg, Marshall; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Watson, James D.
  - TL Cy to Sydney Brenner and F. Jacob, 1961 February 15; 1 item; Meselson, Matthew
    Regarding The Unstable Intermediate manuscript.
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Brenner, Sydney; Editorial matters; Jacob, Francois; Molecular genetics; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc. -- The Unstable Intermediate
  - Summary of Events Leading to Solution of DNA Structure, n.d.; 9.0 p.; Olby, Robert C. (Robert Cecil), 1933-
    10-page timeline.
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; History of biology, especially genetics; Molecular genetics; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - TLS Cy to Dr. James Watson, 1953 March 5; 1 item; Pauling, Linus, 1901-1994
    Protein conference and Pauling's new structure for the nucleic acids.
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Conferences and symposia; Cytogenetics; Delbruck, Max; Molecular genetics; Watson, James D.
  - Rich, Alexander, 1956-1963; 18.0 Item(s)
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Biographical and personal data; Conferences and symposia; Crick, Francis H. C.; Cytogenetics; Gamow, George; Invitations; Laboratory techniques, equipment; Massachusettes Institute of Technology; Molecular genetics; Nirenberg, Marshall; Pauling, Linus; Recommendations -- Warner, Jonathan
    - Folder 1, 1956-1957; 8 items; Rich, Alexander
      RNA backbone; WC structure for DNA; p32 labelling; measurements on various muscle protein fractions; the prospect of DNA's coding for RNA; collagen model; DNA synthesizing system; creating new polymers
    - Folder 2. TL Cy to F. H. C. Crick, 1957-1961; 7 items; Rich, Alexander
      System polyinosinic acid plus polycytidylic acid; poly A coordinates; Russian collagen article; Maurice's DNA coordinates; Pauling-Coring models; Nirenberg system
    - Folder 3. TL Cy to F. H. C. Crick, 1962-1963; 3 items; Rich, Alexander
      Jonathan Warner; polyribosomes; mixed crystals; NMR study of cytidine and deoxycitidine; structure of the guanine-cytosine crystal; finding another complex; in vitro incubation experiments with polyribosomes.
  - Watson, James D., 1953-1955; 5.0 Item(s)
    Biochemistry and organic chemistry; Cytogenetics; Molecular genetics; Teaching -- Pauling, Linus; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
    - Folder 1, 1953 March; 2 items; Watson, James Dewey, 1928-
      Pauling's seminar.
    - Folder 2. ALS Cy to Alex Rich, 1955 March 9; 1 item; Watson, James Dewey, 1928-
      RNA central code
    - Miscellaneous Notes, n.d.; 2 items; Watson, James Dewey, 1928-